Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Water Resources, 1972-1980. (Box-folder 19:11-15)
  - Memoranda, bulletins, and correspondence concerning miscellaneous water issues, 1977-1980., 15 items. (Box-folder 19:15)
    File contains announcement of public meeting on water supply study for Southside Hampton Roads, bulletins on Virginia water laws and quality control, proposed changes in state Water Code, and correspondence regarding possible violations.
  Series 223: Water Resources: Bi-State Commission
- Water Resources: Bi-State Commission, 1978-1982. (Box-folder 19:16-20)
  - Materials relating to work of North Carolina-Virginia Water Resources Management Committee, 1978., 39 items. (Box-folder 19:16)
    Including notification of Bateman's appointment to committee, and agendas, exhibits, and minutes for meetings of 5 June 1978 and 12 June 1978.
  - Memoranda and reports relating to work of North Carolina-Virginia Water Resources Management Committee, June-July 1978., 41 items. (Box-folder 19:17)
    Including agendas, minutes, and working papers for meetings of 21 June and 18 July 1978, and Bateman's handwritten notes of meetings, and reports on Virginia Water Law and long-range water supply needs for Southside of Hampton Roads.
  - Materials relating to work of North Carolina-Virginia Water Resources Management Committee, July-December 1978., 26 items. (Box-folder 19:18)
    Including agendas and minutes of meetings, reports of subcommittees, and publication on southeast United States water resources.
  - Materials relating to work of North Carolina-Virginia Water Resources Management Committee, 1979-1981., 13 items. (Box-folder 19:19)
    Including agendas, minutes and working papers for meetings of 22 May 1979 and 15 December 1981.
  - Materials relating to work of North Carolina-Virginia Water Resources Management Committee, 1982, n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 19:20)
    Including June 1982 draft report, undated summary report on the Chowan River Project, Bateman's handwritten notes on unidentified Committee meeting, and drafts of undated letter to Committee Chairman Maurice B. Rowe.
  Series 224: Water Resources: Potomac
- Correspondence. and reports pertaining to water resources in Northern Virginia and Potomac River, 1976-1977., 7 items. (Box-folder 19:21)
  Including Potomac River Flow Agreement and February 1977 report on potential solutions to water supply problems of Northern Virginia.
  Series 225: Watercraft Sales and Use Tax
- Correspondence, memoranda, reports and legislative materials relating to work of Watercraft Subcommittee, 1980-1981., 20 items. (Box-folder 19:22)
  File contains minutes of subcommittee meetings, Bateman's handwritten notes on meeting and copy of substitute for House bill (H.R. 986) proposing reduction of watercraft sales tax.
  Series 226: Welfare and Institutions
- Welfare and Institutions, 1962-1975. (Box 19-20)
  - Memoranda, correspondence, and reports on miscellaneous welfare issue, 1962-1969., 18 items. (Box-folder 19:23)
    File contains copy of 1966 Housing Bill, copy of 1966 updated section of Virginia Code pertaining to housing, excerpts from Congressional Record(1967) relating to racial ghettos sent to Bateman by U.S. Senator Charles Percy, copy of 1968 paperback book, The Terrible Choice: The Abortion Dilemma, testimony and bulletins on prison reform, and 1969 letter on juvenile delinquency.
    See also files on Abortion, series 1; Corrections, series 29; Juveniles, series 89-92; and Housing Bills, series 77.
  - Two-volume report of the Governor's Study Commission of Vocational Rehabilitation, with executive summary, 1968., 4 items. (Box-folder 19:24)
    See also Rehabilitation and Social Services, series 160.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to welfare issues, 1969-1970., 19 items. (Box-folder 19:25)
    File includes memorandum regarding training school for the mentally retarded, report of the Ecumenical Church Task Group on Equal Opportunity Employment, analysis of President Nixon's welfare proposals by the office of U.S. Senator William Spong, 1969 report on education for hearing impaired children in Virginia, 1970 study of Virginia Corrections Division, and letters and bulletins about abortion.
    See also files on Abortion, series 1; Corrections, series 29; and Rehabilitation and Social Services, series 160.
  - 1971 statistics on state and local shares of welfare costs; 1971 article on day care centers; September 1971 report by state Department of Welfare and Institutions on Virginia's Public Welfare Laws; and June 1971 report from the Virginia White House Conference on Aging; 1971., 5 items. (Box-folder 19:26)
  - Two copies of 1971 report by Division of Youth Services, Services in the Seventies: Virginia's Delinquent Children and Their Families, and legislative proposal for implementation of the Ten Year Plan, 1971., 6 items. (Box-folder 20:1)
  - Correspondence and other materials on miscellaneous welfare issues, 1971-1975., 20 items. (Box-folder 20:2)
    Including constituent letters on abortion, testimony on welfare services, prepared by the Virginia League of Social Services Executives, and Department of Welfare's reply to Bateman's inquiry about responsibility of adult children for their needy parents.
  - Salary figures and personnel description of Virginia's Department of Welfare sent to Bateman upon request by Welfare Commissioner William Lukhard, 1975., 3 items. (Box-folder 20:3)
  Series 227: Welfare for the Elderly
- Correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to welfare services for the elderly in Virginia, 1972-1980., 35 items. (Box-folder 20:4)
  Including 1972 summary of amendments to Social Security Act, 1975 bulletin on public welfare statistics, and January-February 1974 correspondence from adult home administrators protesting the low proposed appropriations for old age assistance.
  Series 228: Welfare Study Commission
- Correspondence and memoranda pertaining to work of Joint subcommittee studying Virginia's welfare system, 1971-1973, n.d., 36 items. (Box-folder 20:5)
  Including 1971-1972 Welfare Department annual report, 1973 summary of welfare programs by Welfare Commissioner William Lukhard, Department's undated [1973] summary report on actions to be taken to improve program administration, statistics on Aid to Dependent Children and other programs, and original and copies of memo on welfare fraud prepared by law student/intern and sent by Bateman to various officials.
  Series 229: Western State Hospital
- Photocopies of documents, relating to contract for construction of Western State Hospital, Staunton, Virginia, and undated memorandum to Bateman explaining the contract, 1946-1960., 11 items. (Box-folder 20:6)
  Series 230: Wetlands
- Wetlands, 1969-1980. (Box-folder 20:7-8)
  - Interim report, Coastal Wetlands of Virginia, by the Virginia Institute of Marine Science, December 1969., 1 item. (Box-folder 20:7)
    See also Coastal Zone Land Management Act/Bill, series 21-22.
  - Summary and recommendations of December 1969 interim report on Virginia's coastal wetlands; 1980 memorandum regarding appointment of a subcommittee to study wetlands issues; and incomplete and unidentified report on wetlands; 1969, 1980, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 20:8)
  Series 231: Wetlands Bills
- Copies of 1982 bills (S. 235 and S. 238) and amendments to amend wetlands section of Virginia Code, with February 1980 memorandum by Bateman, and Bateman's March 1980 letter to Governor John Dalton regarding wetlands bills passed by 1980 General Assembly, 1980-1982., 18 items. (Box-folder 20:9)
  See also Coastal Zone Land Management Act, series 21.
  Series 232: William and Mary, The College of (W&M)
- The College of William and Mary (W&M), 1970-1981. (Box-folder 20:10-12)
  - Correspondence, addresses, and newspapers clippings pertaining to Bateman's campaign against "open" visitation in college dormitories, 1970-1972., 41 items. (Box-folder 20:10)
    File contains Bateman's letter of 16 July 1970 explaining his position, copies of College of William and Mary (W&M) regulations, photocopies from dormitory visitation books, and other "exhibits" sent to Bateman by R. Harvey Chappell, Jr., Chairman of the Committee on Student Affairs, 1970 and 1972 letters from State Attorney General Andrew Miller, copy of 17 March 1971 W&M Flat Hat, and transcripts of Bateman's remarks upon introducing Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24).
    See also Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24), series 175 and Photograph, series 248.
  - Correspondence and enclosures regarding the College of William and Mary (W&M), 1972-1973., 33 items. (Box-folder 20:11)
    File contains correspondence between Bateman and W&M President Thomas A. Graves, concerning a fire at College library, Bateman's 15 May 1972 complaint against approval of dormitory visitation policy contrary to Bateman's earlier efforts, Graves' 24 May 1972 reply, and bulletins concerning inauguration of the College's special programs.
    See also files for Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24), series 175; and VIMS, series 216.
  - Correspondence and newspaper clippings regarding affairs at the College of William and Mary (W&M), 1974-1976., 29 items. (Box-folder 20:12)
    Including 1974 letters to Bateman supporting state appropriations for construction of a new law school building, 1976 letters from William B. Spong, Dean of the Law School, updating affairs at the school, and transcript of Bateman's undated speech (probably 1970-1972) on problems facing Virginia's institutions of higher learning.
  Series 233: Wine Dealers' Franchise
- Letter from Alexandria, Virginia law firm and enclosed proposals for revision of Virginia Code section dealing with beer and wine franchises, 1976., 4 items. (Box-folder 20:13)
  Series 234: Yorktown, Town of
- Correspondence and legal papers pertaining to 1981 suit of Yorktown Trustees against the York County Board of Supervisors., 12 items. (Box-folder 20:14)
  Series 235: Zoning
- Correspondence with and on behalf of Newport News realtor Paul K. Lotz regarding Virginia's zoning laws, 1981., 3 items. (Box-folder 20:15)
  Series 236: Research Materials
- Research Materials, 1968-1975. (Box 20-21)
  - Assorted issues of the University of Virginia News Letter, 1968-1982., 50 items. (Box-folder 20:16)
    See other issues that are located in the Research series.
  - 1960 census report on population and housing in Newport News metropolitan area; 1965 report of state commission to study toll projects financed under State Revenue Bond Act.; 1960, 1965., 2 items. (Box-folder 20:17)
  - Newport News Planning Commission Neighborhood Analysis and Improvement Program for East End, 1966., 1 item. (Box-folder 20:18)
  - December 1966 statistical tables on tax overlapping in the United States; 1967 paper, Toward a Typology of American Cities; 1967 report by the Committee for Economic Development, A Fiscal Program for a Balanced Federalism; 1966-1967., 4 items. (Box-folder 20:19)
  - 1967 reports on modernizing state government by the Committee for Economic Development and by the Chamber of Commerce of the United States; Hampton Roads Jaycees 1968 Community Attitudes Survey; 1969 report on personal income in Virginia; 1967-1969., 7 items. (Box-folder 20:20)
  - Publication by the Virginia Peninsula Industrial Committee, The Virginia Peninsula, 1969., 3 items. (Box-folder 20:21)
  - University of Virginia report, Virginia's Urban Corridor, 1970., 2 items. (Box-folder 20:22)
  - 1970 "Population Panorama" of Newport News; reprint of 1971 article from Texas Law Review on Virginia Senator William Spong; December 1971, Virginia's Urban Corridor, prepared for the Virginia Electric and Power Co.; report on land use control in America; 1971 report of the Virginia Rural Affairs Study Commission; 1971 report, Virginia and Tobacco; 1970-1971., 7 items. (Box-folder 20:23)
  - Report, Commonwealth of Virginia Statistical Information, 1971., 1 item. (Box-folder 20:24)
  - 1972 report by the Virginia Institute of Marine Science on tidal boundaries as legal boundaries; winter 1972 issue of State Government; March 1972 report, Income in Virginia; 1972 report on state appropriations for education; 1972-1974., 4 items. (Box-folder 20:25)
  - Report of the Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia, 1972; report of Virginia Division of War Veteran's Claims, 1972.; reprint of 1972 article in University of Richmond Law Review on the abolition of Dower in Virginia; report on salaries and expenses in 50 state legislatures, 1973; 1972 state publication, Critical Environmental Areas; 1972-1973., 6 items. (Box-folder 20:26)
  - Virginia Peninsula Industrial publication, The Virginia Peninsula, 1972., 2 items. (Box-folder 20:27)
  - Summary of citizen presentations from Fall 1972 Governor's citizen meetings; copy of 1973 address by John R. Swearingen on "The Energy Dilemma;" 1973 report, Virginia Votes for a New Constitution; 1972-1973., 5 items. (Box-folder 21:1)
  - 1973 House and Senate documents on the rights of public employees; land use policies; and list of pardons and reprieves; Chase Manhattan Bank report on the oil industry; 1974 report on higher education and the Virginia Assembly; summer 1975 issue of State Government; and 1975 report on population of Virginia cities and counties; 1973-1975., 7 items. (Box-folder 21:2)
  Series 237: Constituent Correspondence
- Constituent Correspondence, 1971-1982. (Box-folder 21:3-11)
  - Letters received from constituents and carbon copies of Bateman's replies, 1971., 79 items. (Box-folder 21:3)
    Most correspondence pertains to Bateman's efforts on behalf of constituents with legal and financial problems and problems with governmental and corporate bureaucracies.
  - Bateman's correspondence with and on behalf of constituents, 1972., 58 items. (Box-folder 21:4)
    Also contains solicitations for contributions to charitable organizations and Bateman's replies.
  - Letters from constituents and lobbyists with copies of replies, 1977, August 1980-20 January 1981., 80 items. (Box-folder 21:5)
    Letters concern a wide variety of issues, but largest portion pertain to legislation affecting education and rights of retarded citizens. File contains numerous position papers and legislative agendas from lobbying groups.
  - Letters received from constituents and lobbying groups with copies of replies, 21 January 1981-10 February 1981., 81 items. (Box-folder 21:6)
    Most letters concern salaries for teachers and other state employees. Also includes correspondence soliciting Bateman's assistance for constituents.
  - Letters from constituents and lobbying groups, regarding wide variety of issues, including coal shipment, Lee-Jackson-King Day, eligibility for Medicaid, and state employees salaries, 11 February-17 July 1981., 76 items. (Box-folder 21:7)
  - Letters received from constituents and lobbyists with copies of replies, regarding a wide variety of issues and requests for Bateman's intervention on behalf of constituents in legal trouble, 18 July 1981-April 1981., 81 items. (Box-folder 21:8)
  - Letters received from constituents and copies of replies regarding wide variety of legislative issues, October 1981-7 February 1982., 71 items. (Box-folder 21:9)
    Most letters concern tuition assistance grants, veterans' cemeteries, court filing fees, coal severance tax, and, especially, beginning in February 1982, the Assembly vote on the Equal Rights Amendment. File contains some copies of bills and lobbyists' position papers.
    See also other correspondence folders and files on particular subjects.
  - Letters from constituents and lobbyists with copies of replies, regarding wide variety of legislative issues, 8 February-22 February 1982., 134 items. (Box-folder 21:10)
    Most prominent are an intensive campaign on behalf of the Equal Rights Amendment, a few letters on state funding for abortions, teachers' salaries, legal aid for the poor, and a bill regarding United Parcel Service. File includes many copies of bills and mailings from such groups as the League of Women Voters and "Moral Majority."
  - Letters received from constituents and lobbyists with copies of replies, 24 February-April 1982., 82 items. (Box-folder 21:11)
    Largest portion of letters are mass mailings opposing state aid for abortions and regarding bill on taxation of parochial schools. Letters on a variety of legislative issues.
    See also Abortion, series 1.
  Series 238: Constituent Correspondence Form Letters
- Mostly undated master copies of form letters for responding to constituent correspondence, n.d., 43 items. (Box-folder 21:12)
  Series 239: Legislative Correspondence
- Legislative Correspondence, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 21:13-15)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other materials, February-November 1981., 73 items. (Box-folder 21:13)
    Correspondence from lobbyists and constituents on wide variety of issues, resumes for legislative aide positions, background memoranda from National Conference of State Legislatures, and forms for travel reimbursement.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, including letters pertaining to pending legislation, letters and enclosures from constituents and lobbyists and resumes and vitas of job seekers, December 1981., 28 items. (Box-folder 21:14)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, resumes, and clippings sent to Bateman, January-June 1982., 71 items. (Box-folder 21:15)
    File includes letters on specific issues, such as the Equal Rights Amendment and veterans' cemeteries and correspondence seeking Bateman's assistance on behalf of constituents.
  Series 240: 1982 Session-Communications from Governor, et al.
- Session-Communications from Governor, et al., 1982-1984. (Box-folder 21:16-17)
  - Communications from Governor Charles Robb, from members of Virginia Assembly, and from other local, state, and federal officials regarding pending legislation, January-February 1982., 22 items. (Box-folder 21:16)
    File contains Robb's remarks to Assembly committees on 1982-1984 budget; sequence of events and related exhibits pertaining to proposed amendments to state constitution; and correspondence on such issues as Virginia's Conflict of Interest Act, the Reagan "New Federalism" programs and Medicaid cost containment.
  - Communications from Governor Charles Robb and other state officials, regarding such issues as drunk driving, public drunkenness, training for jailers, state welfare budget, relief of Norfolk savings and loans, Medicaid cost containment, and Governor's appointments, February-March 1982., 43 items. (Box-folder 21:17)
  Series 241: 1982 Session-Constituent Problems
- Phone messages, handwritten notes and documents related to Bateman's handling of constituents' problems with governmental agencies, 1982., 20 items. (Box-folder 21:18)
  Series 242: 1982 Session-Constituent Correspondence
- Session-Constituent Correspondence, 1982. (Box-folder 21:19-20)
  - Letters received from constituents and Bateman's form letter reply concerning proposed changes in health care in nursing homes under the Medicaid program, January-July 1982., 27 items. (Box-folder 21:19)
  - Correspondence and enclosed bills from constituents and lobbyists regarding domestic violence bill, insurance issues, nursing issues, Senate page jobs, and labor union issues., 62 items. (Box-folder 21:20)
    Grouped by issue.
  Series 243: 1982 Session-General Correspondence
- Session-General Correspondence, 1982. (Box-folder 21:21-25)
  - Letters and enclosed items from constituents, January-March 1982., 38 items. (Box-folder 21:21)
    Including requests not to raise state taxes, letters concerning care for housing for the mentally retarded and extensive statistical materials from and about Newport News Public Schools.
  - Correspondence from persons and organizations outside Bateman's district, marked "worth looking at," January-March 1982., 28 items. (Box-folder 21:22)
    Contains letter and bills from Virginia Chapter of Americans for Effective Law Enforcement, letters from agricultural groups on agricultural education and research funds in 1982-1984 budget, letters from Virginia Municipal League and Virginia Retail Merchants Association, and handwritten letter from death row inmate inquiring about Bateman's position on the death penalty.
  - Letters and reports from persons and organizations outside Bateman's district, marked "not worth much," January-February 1982., 25 items. (Box-folder 21:23)
    Contains draft legislation from subcommittee to study revision of Family Trust Fund section of Virginia Code, letters and reports on funding needs of Virginia Polytechnic Institute, letter and transcript of statement from Northern Virginia Service Station Dealers Association on proposed gas tax, and letters from governments of Spotsylvania County and City of Virginia Beach.
  - Letters and reports from persons and organizations outside Bateman's district, marked "not worth much," February-March 1982., 48 items. (Box-folder 21:24)
    File contains letters from professors and administrators at state colleges concerning funding; copy of American Transportation Report on transportation needs of the 1980's; correspondence and photocopies of clippings opposing abortion; and packet of promotional materials on the City of Roanoke.
  - Correspondence from persons and organizations outside Bateman's district, March 1982., 60 items. (Box-folder 21:25)
    Items concern tax bill (S. 305) which religious groups claimed would subject churches and Christian schools to government surveillance. Most items are signed form letters.
  Series 244: 1982 Session-Legislative Correspondence
- Correspondence, regarding a Newport News landfill, and Bateman's letter of 22 November 1982 noting his election to U.S. Congress and his resignation from Virginia Senate, August-November 1982., 7 items. (Box-folder 21:26)
  Series 245: 1982 Session-Specific Bill Requests
- Session-Specific Bill Requests, 1982. (Box-folder 21:27-29)
  - Correspondence and enclosed copies of bills from Bateman's constituents requesting action of specific legislation, February-March 1982., 14 items. (Box-folder 21:27)
    Items include taxation on theater receipts, personal property, and cigarettes; workmen's compensation; psychiatric care; and commonwealth attorney's "relief bill."
  - Letters and copies of bills from persons and groups outside Bateman's district, February-March 1982., 47 items. (Box-folder 21:28)
    Items request action on specified legislation. Materials were designated "might be worth looking at" by Bateman's staff. File contains materials concerning length of trucks allowed on state roads, gross receipt taxation, state spending limitations, and Alexandria, Virginia apartments.
  - Correspondence and enclosed copies of bills from persons and groups outside Bateman's district requesting action on specific legislation, February-March 1982., 80 items. (Box-folder 21:29)
    Items marked by Bateman's staff as "not worth much." File contains information on sentencing by judges; taxation on fuels, motor homes, distilleries, advertising, and meals and rooms for transients; northern Virginia condominium conversion, regulation of occupational therapists; and regulation of "look-alike" drugs.
  Series 246: Unidentified Compendium of Bills
- Unidentified Compendium of Bills, n.d. (Box-folder 22:1-2)
  - Unidentified and undated compendium bills introduced into Virginia Senate, n.d., 1 item. Pages 1-85. (Box-folder 22:1)
  - Unidentified and undated compendium of bills introduced into Virginia Senate session, n.d. (Box-folder 22:2)
  Series 247: Bateman's Pocket Appointment Books, 1964-1977
- Bateman's Pocket Appointment Books, 1964-1977. (Box-folder 22:3-9)